Waco Boating and Fishing Club records, Inclusive: 1890-2002, undated, Bulk:1968-1980
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Waco Boating and Fishing Club records
Inclusive: 1890-2002, undated, Bulk:1968-1980
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3794
Waco Boating and Fishing Club
4 document boxes and 2 oversized boxes.
The Waco Boating and Fishing Club records consist of manuscripts collected from 1890 to 2002. These papers contain correspondence, financial papers, legal documents, literary productions, and other printed materials.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Excellent.
Biography/Profile
The Waco Boating and Fishing Club was organized in 1890 as the first social club in Waco city history. Active until 1988, the club focused on providing a family-friendly place to exercise and socialize with other members.
The purpose of the new club was to construct and maintain a place for preserving and canning fish on a site of at least 50 acres. With many city leaders as members, the club had no problem purchasing 50 acres of ground with a lake on site five miles west of Waco for $2,000. Members settled on the name “Fountain Lake” for their new property, and they began improving the site, drilling an artesian well for fresh water, stocking the lake with fish, and building a boat house.
By the 1900s, the club had switched to the name “Fish Pond Club” instead of the longer and clumsier original name. As improvements continued, the 25-year charter granted by the state ran out, and the club was reformed in 1916 February. By now, the area had become a social center for Waco, with special events, dances, dinners, and parties for members, or non-members if they paid an extra fee. Several people were hired as full-time staff members of the club, and a caretaker’s house was built on site for security of the area. As the area became better known, people began referring to the whole area around the club property as “Fish Pond,” so that when the city of Waco annexed the area, the term “Fish Pond” became the official designation of the community.
By 1947, the clubhouse and grounds were in serious need of improvements. Ridgewood Country Club, founded in 1947, had also begun to give the Boating and Fishing Club serious competition for the first time, and at least some members believed they had to shake the “poor man’s club” perception that Fish Pond had acquired over time, compared to Ridgewood. In 1977, after an engineer’s inspection of the clubhouse for structural problems, the club decided to build a new clubhouse, plus other improvements on the grounds, for approximately $500,000. Fish Pond’s massive capital building campaign, undertaken after extensive board meetings, surveys of members, comments, and member meetings, included a clubhouse, swimming pool, tennis courts, jogging path, playground, parking, and a separate building for dressing rooms. Though the club was already $24,000 in debt, they took out more loans to begin the first building phase, and raised dues on their members several times to obtain more money. The new clubhouse opened in 1979 December, but it is unknown how many of the other planned improvements were ever completed.
Since this collection does not have the complete minutes and other narrative documents until the club was dissolved in 1988, the reasons for dissolving the club and selling all property to Ridgewood are not completely known. However, in 1985 the club sold their 38 remaining acres, perhaps minus the land that the caretaker’s house sat on, to their competitor Ridgewood Country Club to pay off the remaining $400,000 principal on their 1978 clubhouse loan. The club voted to dissolve in 1988, with only the board of directors voting, since there were no members other than the board left.
After the club disbanded there were still enough interested people to continue club-related activities in the area. Several pieces of correspondence and research materials date from the post-club time period, when several people worked to obtain a historical marker for the club. A local street was also named for the club, Fish Pond Road, which had to be brought before the city council, and papers from this later time period are also in the collection.
The Waco Boating and Fishing Club stands as the first social club of Waco’s history, and provides insight into the lives and leisure activities of people from that time.
Scope and Content
The Waco Boating and Fishing Club records begins in 1890 with the minute book of the club. The bulk of the collection is between 1969 and 1984, with very few materials dating from the time it was the social center of Waco, in the early to mid 1900s. Documents include correspondence, financial papers, a large amount of literary productions, and some oversized materials. The literary productions and financial documents series are by far the largest series in the collection.
There are several large gaps within this collection. Other than the minute book and several other documents, there is nothing in this collection from 1890 to around 1950. The majority of the collection is from the 1970s, with a small number of materials clustered before and after that time, but no extensive records exist in this collection from any other time.
Arrangement
The Waco Boating and Fishing Club records were completely unorganized before the current finding aid and processing were undertaken. Currently the Waco Boating and Fishing Club Records is arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, II. Legal Documents, III. Financial Documents, IV. Literary Productions, and V. Oversized Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3794. Acquired 1999-09-20
Index Terms
Places
Waco (Tex.) -- Photographs.; Waco (Tex.).
Subjects
Boats and boating -- Texas.; Country clubs -- Texas.; Fishing -- Texas.; Lakes -- Texas.
Genres
Correspondence.; Financial records.; Financial statements.; Legal documents.; Membership lists.; Minutes (Records); Newsletters.; Surveys (documents)
- Correspondence, 1957-2000, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Excellent.
  Biography/Profile
  Series includes correspondence to and from various leaders of the Waco Boating and Fishing Club. Most of the letters have something to do with membership, either giving it up or wanting to continue as members.
  - General, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General, 1971-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General, 1979 February-March (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General, 1979 April-August (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General, 1979 September-December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General, 1980-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General, 2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Stock Certificates, 1965-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stock Certificates, 1976-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Membership Mailings, 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Legal Documents, 1890-2000, undated; 2
  The series includes various official documents generated by the club, the articles of incorporation, and site and survey plans.
  - General, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General, 1968-1998 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - General, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Appraisal Report, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mortgage, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Insurance, 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Surveys, 2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Rules and Regulations, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1890-1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1973-1998 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Fish Pond Club Addition (1 of 3), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fish Pond Club Addition (2 of 3), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Fish Pond Club Addition (3 of 3), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Surveys and Site Plans, 1962-2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Surveys and Site Plans: [Topographical Map], undated (Box 14 OVZ, Folder 10)
  - Surveys and Site Plans: [Fish Pond Road], 1947-1951 (Box 14 OVZ, Folder 11)
  - Surveys and Site Plans: [West Waco], 1918 (Box 14 OVZ, Folder 12)
  - Surveys and Site Plans: [West Waco], 1929 (Box 14 OVZ, Folder 13)
  - Surveys and Site Plans: [Marked Topographical Map], undated (Box 14 OVZ, Folder 14)
  - Surveys and Site Plans: Site Plan (1 of 3), 1962 (Box 14 OVZ, Folder 15)
  - Surveys and Site Plans: Site Plan (2 of 3), 1962 (Box 14 OVZ, Folder 16)
  - Surveys and Site Plans: Site Plan (3 of 3), 1962 (Box 14 OVZ, Folder 17)
- Financial Documents, 1941-2002, undated; 3
  The series includes bills, receipts, and statements from various vendors around Waco, bank statements, and a sampling of stock certificates sold to members. The series is in good to excellent condition.
  - General, 1975-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Outstanding Dues, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Employee Bonus, 1971-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Tax Documents, 1978-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1963-1978 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1983-2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Bank Statements, 1971-May 1979 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bank Statements, 1979 June-September (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bank Statements, 1979 October-December, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements: Building Clubhouse, 1973 January-October (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements: Building Clubhouse, 1978 November-1979 January (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements: Building Clubhouse, 1979 February-June (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements: Building Clubhouse, 1979 July-September (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements: Building Clubhouse, 1979 October-December (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements: Building Clubhouse, 1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Reports, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Reports, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Reports, 1977-1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Reports, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Reports, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Stock Certificates, 1941-1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Stock Certificates, 1950-1957 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Stock Certificates, 1958-1971 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Stock Certificates, 1972-1984, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Stock Certificates, 1971-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Literary Productions, 1890-2000, undated; 4
  The literary productions series, the largest series in the collection, contains notes on a historical marker for the club, membership surveys, minutes, scrapbook pages, and membership lists. The series is in excellent condition.
  - General, 1955-1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - General, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Reports, 1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Fish Pond Road, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Notes, 1970-1979, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Membership Survey and Proposed Improvements, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Newsletters, 1975-1984 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Historical Marker Research Notes, 1890-1941 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Historical Marker Research Notes, 1945-1957 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Historical Marker Research Notes, 1960-1988 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Historical Marker Research Notes, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Historical Marker Research Notes, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Historical Marker Research Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Membership Lists, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Membership Lists, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Membership Lists, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Membership Lists, 1972 January-June (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Membership Lists, 1972 July-December (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Membership Lists, 1973 January-June (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Membership Lists, 1973 July-November (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Membership Lists, 1974 January-June (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Membership Lists, 1974 July-December (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Membership Lists, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Membership Lists, 1976 January-May (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Membership Lists, 1976 June-December (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Membership Lists, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Membership Lists, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Membership Lists, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Membership Lists, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Membership Lists, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Membership Lists, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Membership Lists, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Membership Lists (1 of 2), undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Membership Lists (2 of 2), undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Minutes, 1972-1977 May (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Minutes, 1977 June-November (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Minutes, 1978 January-February (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Minutes, 1978 March-May (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Minutes, 1978 June (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Minutes, 1979 January (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Minutes, 1979 February (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Minutes, 1979 March (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Minutes, 1979 April (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Minutes, 1979 May-June (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Minutes, 1979 August (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Minutes, 1979 October-November (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Book: Minute Book (1 of 7), 1890-1892 June (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Book: Minute Book (2 of 7), 1892-1895 April (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Book: Minute Book (3 of 7), 1895 May-1899 June (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Book: Minute Book (4 of 7), 1899 August-1905 April (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Book: Minute Book (5 of 7), 1905 May-1910 January (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Book: Minute Book (6 of 7), 1910 April-1914 April (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Book: Minute Book (7 of 7), 1914 October-1918 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Book: Minute Book, 1890-1918 (Box 13 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Book: Atlas, 1899 (Box 13 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook (1 of 8), undated (Box 14 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook (2 of 8), undated (Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook (3 of 8), undated (Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook (4 of 8), undated (Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook (5 of 8), undated (Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook (6 of 8), undated (Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook (7 of 8), undated (Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook (8 of 8), undated (Folder 8)
- Photographic Materials, 1946-1964; 5
  This series contains a number of family photographs taken on the Waco Boating and Fishing Club property. Several photographs were taken from the air of the site, but most are of people during various club events.
  - Photographs, 1946-1951 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, 1953-1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1960-1964 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)